How many of you are creatives,
كم مبدع بينكم،
designers, engineers, entrepreneurs, artists,
كم مهندس، مصمم، رجل أعمال، فنان،
Show of hands? (Cheers)
هل ترفعون أيديكم؟ (هتاف)
That's most of you.
أغلبكم.
I have some news for us creatives.
عندي بعض الأخبار لنا كمبدعين.
Over the course of the next 20 years,
على مدى 20 عامًا القادمة،
more will change around the way we do our work
سيتغيرالكثير في ما يخُص الطريقة التي نقوم بها بعملنا
than has happened in the last 2,000.
خلافًا لما حدث في 2000 عام الأخيرة.
In fact, I think we're at the dawn of a new age in human history.
في الحقيقة، أعتقد أننا في فجر عصر جديد من تاريخ البشرية.
Now, there have been four major historical eras defined by the way we work.
حاليًا، هناك أربعة عصور رئيسية تاريخية تمّ تصنيفها وفقًا لطريقة عملنا.
The Hunter-Gatherer Age lasted several million years.
استمر عصر الصيد وجمع الثمار لملايين السنين.
And then the Agricultural Age lasted several thousand years.
ثم دام العصر الزراعي لآلاف السنين.
The Industrial Age lasted a couple of centuries.
ودام العصر الصناعي لبضع قرون.
And now the Information Age has lasted just a few decades.
وحاليًا لقد دام عصر المعلومات لبضع عقود.
And now today, we're on the cusp of our next great era as a species.
واليوم نحن على أعتاب عصرنا العظيم القادم كأجناس بشرية.
Welcome to the Augmented Age.
أهلًا بكم في عصرالتطور.
In this new era, your natural human capabilities are going to be augmented
في هذا العصرالجديد، ستتطور قدراتكم البشرية
by computational systems that help you think,
بفضل الأنظمة الحاسوبية التي تساعدكم على التفكير،
robotic systems that help you make,
والأنظمة الآلية التي تساعدكم على التنفيذ،
and a digital nervous system
وجهاز عصبي رقمي
that connects you to the world far beyond your natural senses.
يربطك بالعالم أبعد من حواسك الطبيعية.
Let's start with cognitive augmentation.
لنبدأ بالتطور المعرفي.
How many of you are augmented cyborgs?
من بينكم انسان آلي ذو قدرات قابلة للتطور؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I would actually argue that we're already augmented.
سأقيم الحجة بأننا بالفعل قابلون للتطور.
Imagine you're at a party,
تخيل أنك في حفلة،
and somebody asks you a question that you don't know the answer to.
ويسألك أحدهم سؤالًا لا تعرف إجابته.
If you have one of these, in a few seconds, you can know the answer.
إذا كان لديك إحدى هذه، خلال ثوانِ، يمكنك معرفة الإجابة.
But this is just a primitive beginning.
ولكن هذه مجرد بداية أولية.
Even Siri is just a passive tool.
حتى سيري مجرد آلة غير واعية.
In fact, for the last three-and-a-half million years,
في الواقع، لمدة الثلاث ونصف مليون سنة الأخيرة،
the tools that we've had have been completely passive.
كانت الأدوات التي لدينا غير واعية تمامًا.
They do exactly what we tell them and nothing more.
كانت تقوم بما نخبرها به ولا شيء أكثر.
Our very first tool only cut where we struck it.
كانت أداتُنا الأولى تقطع حيثما نضربها
The chisel only carves where the artist points it.
يقطع المِنْقاش حيثما يصوبه الفنان.
And even our most advanced tools do nothing without our explicit direction.
وحتى أدواتنا الأكثرتقدمًا، لا تقوم بشيء من دون توجيهنا المحدد.
In fact, to date, and this is something that frustrates me,
في الحقيقة، حتى هذا التاريخ، وهذا شئ يُحبطني،
we've always been limited
لقد كنا دائمًا مقيدين
by this need to manually push our wills into our tools --
بالحاجة إلى الدفع يدويًا بإرادتنا إلى أداوتنا
like, manual, literally using our hands,
مثل، يدويًا، استعمال أيدينا حرفيًا،
even with computers.
حتى مع الحواسيب.
But I'm more like Scotty in "Star Trek."
ولكني أشبه كثيرًا سكوتي في "ستار تريك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I want to have a conversation with a computer.
أريد إجراء محادثة مع حاسوب.
I want to say, "Computer, let's design a car,"
أريد أن أقول، "أيها الحاسوب، لنصمم سيارة،"
and the computer shows me a car.
ويظهر الحاسوب لي سيارة.
And I say, "No, more fast-looking, and less German,"
وأقول، "لا، ذات مظهر سريع أكثر، وغير ألمانية.
and bang, the computer shows me an option.
فرقعة، ويقدم لي الحاسوب خيارًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That conversation might be a little ways off,
قد تكون تلك محادثة غير ممكنة بعض الشيء،
probably less than many of us think,
ربما أقل مما يعتقد الكثير منا،
but right now,
لكن الآن،
we're working on it.
نحن نعمل على ذلك.
Tools are making this leap from being passive to being generative.
تقوم الأدوات بهذه القفزة من كونها غير واعية إلى كونها منتجة.
Generative design tools use a computer and algorithms
تستخدم أدوات التصميم المُنتجة حاسوب وخوارزميات
to synthesize geometry
لتشكيل هندسة
to come up with new designs all by themselves.
تأتي بتصاميم ذاتية جديدة.
All it needs are your goals and your constraints.
كل ما تحتاجه هو أهدافك وتعليماتك.
I'll give you an example.
سأعطيكم مثالًا.
In the case of this aerial drone chassis,
في حالة هيكل الطائرة بدون طيار هذه،
all you would need to do is tell it something like,
كل ما عليك فعله هو أن تخبره شيئًا مثل،
it has four propellers,
أن لديه أربع أعمدة،
you want it to be as lightweight as possible,
تريدها أن تكون خفيفة الوزن قدر الإمكان،
and you need it to be aerodynamically efficient.
وتريدها أن تكون ذات فاعلية ديناميكية هوائية.
Then what the computer does is it explores the entire solution space:
ما يقوم به الحاسوب هو استكشاف نطاق الحل كاملًا:
every single possibility that solves and meets your criteria --
كل إمكانية ستحل وتلبي معاييرك --
millions of them.
الملايين منهم.
It takes big computers to do this.
يتطلب هذا حواسيب كبيرة.
But it comes back to us with designs
لكن الأمر يعود إلينا بالنسبة للتصاميم
that we, by ourselves, never could've imagined.
التي لم نكن، بأنفسنا، نتخيلها.
And the computer's coming up with this stuff all by itself --
وتقوم الحواسيب بذلك الأمر بذاتها بشكل كامل --
no one ever drew anything,
لم يرسم أحد أي شيء.
and it started completely from scratch.
وبدأت تمامًا من الصفر.
And by the way, it's no accident
وبالمناسبة، ليست صدفة
that the drone body looks just like the pelvis of a flying squirrel.
أن يشبه هيكل الطائرة بدون طيار حوض السنجاب الطائر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's because the algorithms are designed to work
ذلك لأن الخوارزميات صُمّمت للعمل
the same way evolution does.
بنفس طريقة التطور.
What's exciting is we're starting to see this technology
المثير أننا بدأنا نرى هذه التكنولوجيا
out in the real world.
جَلية في العالم الواقعي.
We've been working with Airbus for a couple of years
لقد عملنا مع أيرباص لعدة سنوات
on this concept plane for the future.
على مفهوم الطائرة هذا للمستقبل.
It's a ways out still.
لم ترَ النور بعد.
But just recently we used a generative-design AI
لكن مؤخرًا، استخدمنا تصميم ذو ذكاء اصطناعي مُنتج.
to come up with this.
ليأتي بهذا.
This is a 3D-printed cabin partition that's been designed by a computer.
هذا قسم مقصورة ذات صورة ثلاثية أبعاد صممها حاسوب.
It's stronger than the original yet half the weight,
إنها أقوى من الحقيقية و تزن نصف الوزن الحقيقي،
and it will be flying in the Airbus A320 later this year.
وستطير في إيرباص A320 لاحقًا هذا العام.
So computers can now generate;
لذا يمكن للحواسيب أن تنتج الآن؛
they can come up with their own solutions to our well-defined problems.
يمكنها تقديم حلولها الخاصة لمشاكلنا المحددة.
But they're not intuitive.
ولكنها ليست بديهية.
They still have to start from scratch every single time,
فلا يزال عليها البدء من الصفر كل مرّة،
and that's because they never learn.
ذلك لأنها لا تتعلم أبدًا.
Unlike Maggie.
على عكس ماجي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maggie's actually smarter than our most advanced design tools.
ماجي في الحقيقة أذكى من أدواتنا التصمّيمة الأكثر تقدمًا.
What do I mean by that?
ما الذي أعنيه بذلك؟
If her owner picks up that leash,
إذا التقط صاحبها الرسن،
Maggie knows with a fair degree of certainty
تعرف ماجي بدرجة كبيرة من التأكد
it's time to go for a walk.
أنه حان وقت الذهاب للتنزه.
And how did she learn?
وكيف تعلمت ذلك؟
Well, every time the owner picked up the leash, they went for a walk.
حسنًا، كلما يلتقط صاحبها الرسن، يذهبان للتنزه.
And Maggie did three things:
وقامت ماجي بثلاثة أشياء:
she had to pay attention,
كانت لابد أن تنتبه،
she had to remember what happened
وكانت لابد أن تتذكر ما حدث
and she had to retain and create a pattern in her mind.
وكان عليها أن تحفظ مسارًا في رأسها وتحدده.
Interestingly, that's exactly what
والمثير للاهتمام، هذا هو بالضبط
computer scientists have been trying to get AIs to do
يحاول علماء الحاسوب جَعل الذكاء الإصطناعي يقوم بذلك
for the last 60 or so years.
لمدة 60 سنة الأخيرة أو ما يُقارب ذلك.
Back in 1952,
بالعودة لعام 1952،
they built this computer that could play Tic-Tac-Toe.
صنعوا هذا الحاسوب الذي يصدر صوت تيك-تاك-تو
Big deal.
أمر عظيم.
Then 45 years later, in 1997,
ثم بعد 45 سنة، في عام 1997،
Deep Blue beats Kasparov at chess.
هزم ديب بلو كاسباروف في لعبة الشطرنج.
2011, Watson beats these two humans at Jeopardy,
في 2011، هزم واتسون هذان البشريان في جاباردي،
which is much harder for a computer to play than chess is.
وهو شيء أصعب للحاسوب في اللعب من الشطرنج.
In fact, rather than working from predefined recipes,
في الحقيقة،
Watson had to use reasoning to overcome his human opponents.
احتاج وتسون لاستخدام المنطق حتى يتغلب على خصومه البشريين.
And then a couple of weeks ago,
ومن ثم منذ بضعة أسابيع،
DeepMind's AlphaGo beats the world's best human at Go,
هزم ديب ميند التابع لألفاجو أفضل بشري في جو،
which is the most difficult game that we have.
والتى تعد أصعب لعبة لدينا.
In fact, in Go, there are more possible moves
في الحقيقة، في جو، هناك المزيد من التغيرات الممكنة
than there are atoms in the universe.
أكثر من الذرات الموجودة في الكون.
So in order to win,
لذا للفوز،
what AlphaGo had to do was develop intuition.
يجب على الفاجو أن يقوم بتطوير البديهة.
And in fact, at some points, AlphaGo's programmers didn't understand
وفي الواقع، في بعض النقاط، لم يفهم مبرمجو الفاجو
why AlphaGo was doing what it was doing.
لما كان يقوم ألفاجو بما قام به.
And things are moving really fast.
وتمضي الأشياء بسرعة كبيرة.
I mean, consider -- in the space of a human lifetime,
أعني، فكروا في -- في نطاق العمر البشري،
computers have gone from a child's game
فقد انتقلت الحواسيب من كونها لعبة أطفال
to what's recognized as the pinnacle of strategic thought.
إلى كونها رأس التفكير الاستراتيجي.
What's basically happening
ما يحدث أساسيًا
is computers are going from being like Spock
هو أن الحواسيب تنتقل من كونها شبه سبوك
to being a lot more like Kirk.
إلى كونها أكثر شبهًا بكيرك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right? From pure logic to intuition.
صحيح؟ من المنطق البحت إلى البديهة.
Would you cross this bridge?
هل ستعبرون هذا الجسر؟
Most of you are saying, "Oh, hell no!"
يقول معظمكم، "اوه، لا بحق الجحيم!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you arrived at that decision in a split second.
وقد قررتم ذلك في جزء أقل من الثانية.
You just sort of knew that bridge was unsafe.
تعرفون نوعًا ما بأن هذا الجسر غير آمن.
And that's exactly the kind of intuition
وهذا بالتحديد هو البديهة
that our deep-learning systems are starting to develop right now.
التي بدأت أنظمتنا المعرفيّة المعقدة بتطويرها الآن.
Very soon, you'll literally be able
قريبًا، ستكونون حرفيًا قادرين على
to show something you've made, you've designed,
أن تظهروا شيء قد صنعتموه، أو صممتموه،
to a computer,
إلى حاسوب،
and it will look at it and say,
وسينظر إليه ويقول،
"Sorry, homie, that'll never work. You have to try again."
"آسف، يا صاح، لن يصلح هذا أبدًا. لابد أن تحاول مجددًا.
Or you could ask it if people are going to like your next song,
أو قد تساله إذا ما كان الناس سيحبون أُغنيتك التالية،
or your next flavor of ice cream.
او نكهتك التالية من الآيس كريم.
Or, much more importantly,
أو ما هو أكثر أهميةً من ذلك،
you could work with a computer to solve a problem
هو العمل مع حاسوب لحل مشكلة
that we've never faced before.
لم نواجهها من قبل.
For instance, climate change.
على سبيل المثال، تغير المناخ.
We're not doing a very good job on our own,
نحن لا نقوم بعمل جيد بمفردنا،
we could certainly use all the help we can get.
يمكننا بالتاكيد استخدام المساعدة التي يمكن أن نحصل عليها.
That's what I'm talking about,
هذا ما أتحدث عنه،
technology amplifying our cognitive abilities
تقوي التكنولوجيا قدراتنا الإدراكية
so we can imagine and design things that were simply out of our reach
بذلك يمكننا تخيل وتصميم أشياء لم تكن في متناولنا
as plain old un-augmented humans.
كبشر غير متطورين وبسطاء.
So what about making all of this crazy new stuff
إذاً ماذا عن هذا الشيء المجنون الجديد
that we're going to invent and design?
الذي سنخترعه وسنصممه؟
I think the era of human augmentation is as much about the physical world
أعتقد أن عصر التطور البشري بقدر ما هو حول العالم المادي
as it is about the virtual, intellectual realm.
بقدر ما هو حول العالم الإفتراضي الفكري.
How will technology augment us?
إذًا كيف ستتطورنا التكنولوجيا؟
In the physical world, robotic systems.
في العالم المادي، الأنظمة الآلية.
OK, there's certainly a fear
حسنًا، هناك بالتأكيد خوف من
that robots are going to take jobs away from humans,
أن الأنظمة الحاسوبية ستأخذ وظائف البشر،
and that is true in certain sectors.
وهذا حقيقي في بعض القطاعات.
But I'm much more interested in this idea
ولكني مهتم أكثر بهذه الفكرة
that humans and robots working together are going to augment each other,
أن عمل البشر والأنسان الآلي معًا سيطور من بعضهم البعض،
and start to inhabit a new space.
ويبدأون بشغل مجال جديد.
This is our applied research lab in San Francisco,
هذا معملنا للبحث التطبيقي في سان فرانسيسكو،
where one of our areas of focus is advanced robotics,
حيث أحدى مجالات اهتماماتنا هو علم الإنسان الآلي المتقدم،
specifically, human-robot collaboration.
وبالأخص، التعاون البشري الآلي.
And this is Bishop, one of our robots.
وهذا بيشوب، إنسان آلي لدينا.
As an experiment, we set it up
كتجربة، أعددناه
to help a person working in construction doing repetitive tasks --
لمساعدة شخص يعمل في البناء يقوم بمهام متكررة --
tasks like cutting out holes for outlets or light switches in drywall.
مهام مثل حفر ثقوب مأخذ التيار أو مفاتيح الإضاءة في حائط الجبس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, Bishop's human partner can tell what to do in plain English
فالشريك البشري لبيشوب بإمكانه إخباره بما يجب فعله بإنجليزية بسيطة
and with simple gestures,
وبإشارات بسيطة،
kind of like talking to a dog,
نوعًا ما مثل التحدث إلى كلب،
and then Bishop executes on those instructions
وبعدها ينفذ بيشوب وفقًا لتلك التعليمات
with perfect precision.
بإحكام تام.
We're using the human for what the human is good at:
نحن نستخدم البشر فيما هم جيدون فيه:
awareness, perception and decision making.
الوعي و الإدراك واتخاذ القررات،
And we're using the robot for what it's good at:
ونستخدم الإنسان الآلي فيما هو جيد فيه:
precision and repetitiveness.
الانضباط والتكرار.
Here's another cool project that Bishop worked on.
وهنا مشروع ممتاز آخر يعمل به بيشوب.
The goal of this project, which we called the HIVE,
إن هدف هذا المشروع، الذي نسميه ال "هايف"،
was to prototype the experience of humans, computers and robots
هو وضع تصميم أولي لتجربة البشر والحواسيب والإنسان الآلي
all working together to solve a highly complex design problem.
لعملهم معًا جميعًا لحل مشكلة تصميم معقدة جدًا.
The humans acted as labor.
يمثل البشر العمالة.
They cruised around the construction site, they manipulated the bamboo --
هم يتجولون حول موقع البناء، ويشكلون الخيزران --
which, by the way, because it's a non-isomorphic material,
والذي بسبب كونه مادة غير تَشاكُلية،
is super hard for robots to deal with.
صعب جدًا على الإنسان الآلي التعامل معها.
But then the robots did this fiber winding,
من ثم يقوم الإنسان الآلي بلف الألياف هذه،
which was almost impossible for a human to do.
والذي كان مستحيل تقريبًا علي البشر فعله.
And then we had an AI that was controlling everything.
ومن ثم كان لدينا الذكاء الصنعي الذي يتحكم في كل شيء.
It was telling the humans what to do, telling the robots what to do
كان يُملي على البشرما يجب عليهم فعله، والإنسان الآلي كذلك
and keeping track of thousands of individual components.
ويتتبع مسار آلاف المكونات الفردية.
What's interesting is,
المثير للاهتمام أن،
building this pavilion was simply not possible
بناء هذا الجناح لم يكن ممكنًا
without human, robot and AI augmenting each other.
بدون البشر والإنسان الآلي و الذكاء الصنعي بتطويرهم لبعضهم البعض.
OK, I'll share one more project. This one's a little bit crazy.
حسنًا، سأشارككم مشروع آخر. و هو مجنون قليلًا.
We're working with Amsterdam-based artist Joris Laarman and his team at MX3D
إننا نعمل مع فنان مقيم في أمستردام جوريس لارمان وفريقه في أم أكس ثري دي
to generatively design and robotically print
وذلك للتصميم بشكل إنتاجي والطباعة آليًا
the world's first autonomously manufactured bridge.
أول جسر في العالم مصنع بشكل استقلالي.
So, Joris and an AI are designing this thing right now, as we speak,
وبذلك، يصمم جوريس و الذكاء الصنعي هذا الشيء الآن، ونحن نتكلم،
in Amsterdam.
في أمستردام.
And when they're done, we're going to hit "Go,"
وعندما ينتهون، سنعطي "إشارة البدء"
and robots will start 3D printing in stainless steel,
وسيبدأ الإنسان الآلي برسم رسومات ثلاثية الأبعاد على فولاذ مقاوم للصدأ.
and then they're going to keep printing, without human intervention,
وبعدها سيواصلون الرسم من دون تدخل البشر،
until the bridge is finished.
حتي ينتهي الجسر.
So, as computers are going to augment our ability
لذا إن كانت الحواسيب ستطور من قدرتنا
to imagine and design new stuff,
على تخيل وتصمم أشياء جديدة،
robotic systems are going to help us build and make things
فستساعدنا النُظم الآلية على بناء وتصنيع أشياء جديدة
that we've never been able to make before.
لم نكن قادرين على القيام بها من قبل.
But what about our ability to sense and control these things?
ولكن ماذا عن قدرتنا على الإدراك والتحكم في هذه الأشياء؟
What about a nervous system for the things that we make?
ماذا عن جهاز عصبي للأشياء التى نصنعها؟
Our nervous system, the human nervous system,
جهازنا العصبي، الجهازي العصبي البشري،
tells us everything that's going on around us.
يخبرنا بالأشياء التى تجري من حولنا.
But the nervous system of the things we make is rudimentary at best.
لكن الجهاز العصبي للأشياء التي نصنعها بدائي في أحسن حالاته.
For instance, a car doesn't tell the city's public works department
مثلًا، السيارة لا تُخبر دائرة الأشغال العامة بالمدينة
that it just hit a pothole at the corner of Broadway and Morrison.
أنها قد اصطدمت في حفرة عند زاوية برودواي و إيمرسون.
A building doesn't tell its designers
وأن البناء لا يخبر مصمميه
whether or not the people inside like being there,
إن ما كان الناس بداخله يحبون التواجد فيه أم لا،
and the toy manufacturer doesn't know
ولايعرف مصمم لعُبة
if a toy is actually being played with --
إن كان يُلعب بها --
how and where and whether or not it's any fun.
كيف وأين وإذا ما كانت ممتعة أو لا.
Look, I'm sure that the designers imagined this lifestyle for Barbie
انظروا، أنا متأكد أن المصممين تخيلوا نظام الحياة هذا لباربي
when they designed her.
وهم يصممونها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what if it turns out that Barbie's actually really lonely?
لكن ماذا لو بدا أن باربي في الواقع وحيدة؟
If the designers had known
لو كان يعلم المصممون
what was really happening in the real world
ما كان يحدث في العالم الواقعي
with their designs -- the road, the building, Barbie --
مع تصميماتهم -- الطريق، البناء، باربي --
they could've used that knowledge to create an experience
لكانوا استخدموا هذه المعرفة لخلق تجربة
that was better for the user.
أفضل للمستخدم.
What's missing is a nervous system
ما ينقص هو جهاز عصبي
connecting us to all of the things that we design, make and use.
يربطنا بجميع الأشياء التي نُصممها ونصنعها ونستخدمها.
What if all of you had that kind of information flowing to you
ماذا لو كان لديكم هذا النوع من المعلومات التي تأتي اليكم
from the things you create in the real world?
من الأشياء التي تصنعونها في العالم الواقعي.
With all of the stuff we make,
مع كل هذه الأشياء التي نصنعها،
we spend a tremendous amount of money and energy --
قد أنفقنا كم هائل من المال والطاقة --
in fact, last year, about two trillion dollars --
فى الواقع، العام الماضي، حوالي 2 تريليون دولارًا --
convincing people to buy the things we've made.
لإقناع الناس بشراء الأشياء التي صنعناها .
But if you had this connection to the things that you design and create
لكن إن كان لديكم هذه العلاقة بين الأشياء التي تصممونها وتصنعونها
after they're out in the real world,
بعدما كانوا في العالم الخارجي،
after they've been sold or launched or whatever,
بعد بيعهم أو اطلاقهم أو أيًا كان،
we could actually change that,
بإمكاننا فعليًا تغيير ذلك،
and go from making people want our stuff,
ونتحول من جذب الناس لشراء أشياءنا،
to just making stuff that people want in the first place.
إلى تصنيع الأشياء التي يريدها الناس في المقام الأول.
The good news is, we're working on digital nervous systems
الأخبار الجيدة هى أننا نعمل على جهاز عصبي رقمي
that connect us to the things we design.
يربطنا بالأشياء التي نصممها.
We're working on one project
نعمل على مشروع
with a couple of guys down in Los Angeles called the Bandito Brothers
مع بعض الرفاق في لوس أنجلوس يسمون "بانديتو برازرز"
and their team.
وفريقهم.
And one of the things these guys do is build insane cars
وأحد الأشياء التي يقوم بها هؤلاء الرفاق هو تصميم سيارات مجنونة
that do absolutely insane things.
والتي تقوم بالطبع بأشياء مجنونة.
These guys are crazy --
هؤلاء الرفاق مجانين--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
in the best way.
بأفضل حال.
And what we're doing with them
وما نفعله معهم
is taking a traditional race-car chassis
هو أخد هيكل سيارة سباق تقليدية
and giving it a nervous system.
وإعطاءه جهاز عصبي.
So we instrumented it with dozens of sensors,
وعليه فقد جهزها بعشرات من أجهزة الاستشعار،
put a world-class driver behind the wheel,
وجعلنا سائق ذو تصنيف عالمي يقودها،
took it out to the desert and drove the hell out of it for a week.
وأخذها خارجًا الى الصحراء وقادها لمدة أسبوع.
And the car's nervous system captured everything
والتقط الجهاز العصبي للسيارة كل شيء
that was happening to the car.
كان يحدث للسيارة.
We captured four billion data points;
لقد جمعنا 4 بليون نقطة معلومات؛
all of the forces that it was subjected to.
جميعها من القوى التي خضعت لها.
And then we did something crazy.
وبعدها قمنا بشيء مجنون.
We took all of that data,
أخذنا كل تلك المعلومات،
and plugged it into a generative-design AI we call "Dreamcatcher."
ووصلناها الى تصميم إنتاجي للذكاء الصنعي أسميناه " دريمكاتشر."
So what do get when you give a design tool a nervous system,
إذًأ ماذا يحدث عندما تعطي جهاز عصبي لآلة تصميم،
and you ask it to build you the ultimate car chassis?
وطلبت منها أن تصمم لك هيكل سيارة نهائي؟
You get this.
ستحصل على هذا.
This is something that a human could never have designed.
هذا شيء لم يمكن لإنسان أن يصممه أبدًا.
Except a human did design this,
باستثناء إنسان واحد قام بتصميمه،
but it was a human that was augmented by a generative-design AI,
لكنه كان إنسان قد تطورعن طريق تصميم إنتاجي للذكاء الصنعي،
a digital nervous system
و نظام عصبي رقمي
and robots that can actually fabricate something like this.
و إنسان آلي بإمكانه أن يصنع شيء مثل هذا.
So if this is the future, the Augmented Age,
لذا، إذا كان هذا هو المستقبل، والعصر المتطور
and we're going to be augmented cognitively, physically and perceptually,
وسنتطور معرفيًا وماديًا وإدراكيًا،
what will that look like?
كيف سيبدوا هذا؟
What is this wonderland going to be like?
كيف ستبدو أرض العجائب هذه؟
I think we're going to see a world
أعتقد أننا سنرى عالم
where we're moving from things that are fabricated
حيث سننتقل من الأشياء المصنعة
to things that are farmed.
الى الأشياء المزروعة.
Where we're moving from things that are constructed
وحيث سننتقل من الأشياء المبنية
to that which is grown.
إلى تلك النامية.
We're going to move from being isolated
سنتحول من كوننا منعزلين
to being connected.
إلى كوننا متواصلين.
And we'll move away from extraction
وسنبتعد عن الاستخراج
to embrace aggregation.
إلى قبول التجميع.
I also think we'll shift from craving obedience from our things
أعتقد أيضًا أننا سنغير من الرغبة في انقياد الأشياء لنا
to valuing autonomy.
إلى تقدير التحكم الذاتي.
Thanks to our augmented capabilities,
بفضل قدراتنا المطورة،
our world is going to change dramatically.
سيتغيرعالمنا بشكل كبير.
We're going to have a world with more variety, more connectedness,
سيكون لدينا عالم ذو تنوع أكثر، وذو اتصال أكبر،
more dynamism, more complexity,
وذو دينامكية أكثر، وتعقيد أكبر،
more adaptability and, of course,
وأكثر تكيفًا، وبالطبع،
more beauty.
أكثر جمالًا.
The shape of things to come
شكل الأشياء المستقبلية
will be unlike anything we've ever seen before.
سيكون مختلف عن الأشياء التي رأيناها من قبل.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because what will be shaping those things is this new partnership
لأن من سيشكل تلك الأشياء هي تلك الشراكة الجديدة
between technology, nature and humanity.
بين التكنولوجيا والطبيعة والإنسانية.
That, to me, is a future well worth looking forward to.
ذلك، بالنسبة لي، مستقبل جدير بأن يُتطلع إليه.
Thank you all so much.
الشكر لكم جميعًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)